{"tossups": [{"question": "This U.S. immigrant's early ventures included investments in Adams Express and the founding of the Keystone Bridge Company. After selling his largest company to J.P. Morgan, this author of the \"Gospel of Wealth\" created a namesake foundation to establish libraries and research councils. Making most of his wealth as a steel magnate, for ten points, what Scottish-born American philanthropist built an eponymous concert hall in New York City?", "answer": "Andrew <b><u>Carnegie</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Cave paintings in the Acacus [[ah-KAH-kus]] Mountains indicate this desert may only have formed after the last Ice Age. The Tibesti mountains lie in this desert, which in recent decades has advanced south into the Sahel [[sah-HEEL]]. Peoples including the Berbers and the Tuareg [[TWAH-reg]] led gold and salt caravans across this desert. Historically crossed by Bedouin caravans, for ten points, what is this massive desert in northern Africa?", "answer": "<b><u>Sahara</u></b> Desert (or a\u1e63-<b><u>\u1e63</u><u>a</u><u>\u1e25</u><u>r</u><u>\u0101\u02bc</u></b> al-kubr\u00e1) (3) This woman's actions at Werowocomoco [[way-ruh-wah-KOH-muh-koh]] are detailed in a letter to Queen Anne of Denmark. This woman died after travelling to England with her husband, John Rolfe, ten years after she intervened in an execution ordered by her father, the Powhatan [[POW-uh-tan]] chief. For ten points, name this Native American \"princess\" who supposedly saved the life of John Smith during the first year of Jamestown. ANSWER: <b><u>Pocahontas</u></b> (accept <b><u>Matoaka</u></b>; accept Rebecca <b><u>Rolfe</u></b> before \"Rolfe\" is mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This structure's \"Robber's Tunnel\" was likely resealed during the Ramesside Restoration, one of many ancient sites refurbished by the sitting government. At the foot of this structure is a preserved solar barque [[BARK]] known as Khufu's Ship. First built in the 26th Century BC, this building stood as the tallest structure in the world until the construction of the Lincoln Cathedral in 1311. For ten points, name this Egyptian tomb and \"Ancient Wonder of the World.\"", "answer": "<b><u>Great Pyramid</u></b> of Giza (accept <b><u>Pyramid</u></b> of <b><u>Khufu</u></b>; or <b><u>Pyramid</u></b> of <b><u>Cheops</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "During this conflict, the<em> The Sun</em>'s headline \"Gotcha\" caused controversy for downplaying its casualties. Operation Rosario, ordered by Leopoldo Galtieri [[gahl-TYEH-ree]], began this war, which included an engagement between the<em> General</em> <em>Belgrano</em> and the HMS<em> Conqueror</em>. Margaret Thatcher and her War Cabinet quickly recaptured South Georgia during this conflict. The UK and Argentina vied for control of a namesake Atlantic archipelago in, for ten points, what ten-week war in 1982?", "answer": "<b><u>Falkland</u></b>s Wars (accept War of the <b><u>Falkland</u></b> Islands; accept La Guerra de las <b><u>Malvinas</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "A member of this religious sect named Alice Paul served as president of the National Women's Party. The only U.S. president to follow this denomination's teachings was Richard Nixon. This sect's persecution in England led William Penn to request that James II give him and his followers land in the New World. For ten points, name this pacifist Christian sect more formally known as the Society of Friends.", "answer": "<b><u>Quaker</u></b>s (accept Society of <b><u>Friends</u></b> before mentioned; prompt on \"Christianity\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This politician openly criticized fellow party member Joe Manchin for using the term \"young lady\" while refuting her claims on his lack of transparency in negotiating with oil lobbyists. This congresswoman, who wore a dress emblazoned with the words \"Tax the Rich\" to the 2021 Met Gala, is the youngest woman to take a seat in the House of Representatives, at the age of 29. For ten points, name this Puerto Rican-descended New York Representative sometimes known by her initials AOC.", "answer": "Alexandria <b><u>Ocasio-Cortez</u></b> (accept <b><u>AOC</u></b> before mentioned; prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This musician, who embarked on the Never Ending Tour in 1988, released the 1979 album<em> Slow Train Coming</em> following his conversion to Evangelical Christianity. This artist included \"A Hard Rain's a-Gonna Fall\" on his seminal album titled<em> The Freewheelin'</em> [this artist]. The author of such folk hits as \"The Times They Are a-Changin'\" and \"Blowin' in the Wind,\" for ten points, who is this winner of the 2016 Nobel Prize in Literature?", "answer": "Bob <b><u>Dylan</u></b> (accept Robert <b><u>Dylan</u></b>; accept Robert Allen <b><u>Zimmerman</u></b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "In this city, millwright Rufus Putnam created effective prefabricated fortifications prior to the battle of Dorchester Heights. Henry Knox dragged cannons captured at Fort Ticonderoga to assist in Washington's capture of this city. William Prescott and Israel Putnam led a failed defense of Breed's Hill during Thomas Gage's 1775 assault on this city. A 1770 \"Massacre\" occurred in, for ten points, what New England city, the site of the Battle of Bunker Hill?", "answer": "<b><u>Boston</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "Using an aquarium, filmmaker Georges M\u00e9li\u00e8s [[mel-YAY]] simulated exploring this ship's wreckage in a 19th century silent short film. The 1898 Del Peral [[peh-RAHL]] Inquiry found that this ship's demise was not caused by hitting a mine. In an example of \"yellow journalism,\" this ship's name was rhymed with the phrase \"To Hell with Spain\" by the U.S. press. For ten points, name this cruiser whose sinking in Havana Harbor was an impetus for the Spanish-American War.", "answer": "USS <em><b><u>Maine</u></b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man made a 300-mile long journey to Delagoa Bay following his escape from a Boer prison camp. The disaster of the Dardanelles campaign, especially the Battle of Gallipoli [[gah-LIH-poh-lee]], led to this man's resignation as First Lord of the Admiralty. Following the Dunkirk evacuation, this PM gave the \"This was their finest hour\" speech to the House of Commons. For ten points, name this prime minister of the UK during the majority of World War Two.", "answer": "Winston <b><u>Churchill</u></b> (or Sir Winston Leonard Spencer <b><u>Churchill</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This politician had three electoral votes cast for him in the 2016 election from the state of Washington. This man became National Security Adviser for Reagan in the wake of the Iran-Contra Scandal. Following the January Capitol attacks, this politician publicly left the Republican Party. This man died from COVID-19 complications at Walter Reed hospital in October of 2021. The Secretary of State during the first George W. Bush administration was, for ten points, which four-star general?", "answer": "Colin <b><u>Powell</u></b> (or Colin Luther <b><u>Powell</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In this nation,<em> Inaka</em> [[ee-NAH-kah]] is a term for people who live in small hamlets far from major metropolitan areas. An eighth-century Shugendo monk was the first to summit one of this nation's \"Three Holy Mountains,\" Mount Haku. Every twenty years, this nation's pilgrimage site, the Ise [[EE-seh]] Grand Shrine, is rebuilt to represent death and renewal in the Shinto faith. The cities of Osaka and Nagasaki are found in, for ten points, what East Asian nation?", "answer": "<b><u>Japan</u></b> (accept <b><u>Nippon</u></b>-koku or <b><u>Nihon</u></b>-koku)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Ne Win of Myanmar may have been trained by the last of these people. Ten of</u> <u>these people formed a group of \"Braves,\" and some used a tool named for \"water</u> <u>spiders.\" In one incident, these people replicated Mon lamps in (+)</u> an attack. Nightingale floors were intended to expose these people, whose training likely originated with the Iga clan in the Kansai region. Often shown with star-shaped (*) </b><em>shuriken</em>, for ten points, who were these stealthy Japanese mercenaries?", "answer": "<b><u>Ninja</u></b> (accept <b><u>Shinobi</u></b>; <b><u>Monomi</u></b>; or <b><u>Nokizaru</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This city celebrates Three Flags Day, which commemorates the two days in</u> <u>1804 on which the French, Spanish, and U.S. flags flew over it during the Louisiana</u> <u>Purchase. This host of the (+)</u> 1904 Olympics is near Cahokia Mounds and contains a monument to westward expansion, the Gateway (*)</b> Arch. A French king is the namesake of, for ten points, what largest city in Missouri?", "answer": "<b><u>St. Louis</u></b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>In this nation, the</u></b><em><b><u> nau</u></b></em><b><u> cargo ship known as</u></b><em><b><u> Nossa Senhora</u></b></em><b><u> sank in its longest</u> <u>river while carrying peppercorns back from India. In the 15th century, Afonso III from</u> <u>the House of Aviz styled himself ruler of this one-time (+)</u> kingdom and the recently conquered region of Algarve [[al-GAR-veh]]. The expedition to Ceuta [[seh-YOO-tah]] was launched from this nation's city of Porto by Henry the Navigator. (*)</b> For the point, identify this European country on the Iberian Peninsula, governed from Lisbon.", "answer": "<b><u>Portugal</u></b> (accept <b><u>Portuguese</u></b> Republic; or Rep\u00fablica <b><u>Portuguesa</u></b>); accept Kingdom of <b><u>Portugal</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>A group of Democrats with this name nominated former Republican John M.</u> <u>Palmer as their presidential candidate in 1896. An 1869 \"Panic\" over this good</u> <u>occurred after investors Jay Gould and James (+)</u> Fisk attempted to corner its market. At the 1896 DNC, bimetallism supporter William Jennings Bryan delivered a speech stating \"you shall not crucify mankind upon a cross of\" (*)</b> [this good]. For ten points, name this precious metal whose \"Standard\" was abandoned by Richard Nixon.", "answer": "<b><u>Gold</u></b> (accept <b><u>Au</u></b>; accept <b><u>Gold</u></b> Democrats; accept \"Cross of <b><u>Gold</u></b>\" speech)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This figure may have invented the plot in which Royalist C\u00e9cile Renault</u> <u>[[ray-NOH]] hid two small knives in a bag in an attempt to kill him. With support from</u> <u>the Garde National, the faction known as the Thermidorians ousted (+)</u> this man and sent him to the guillotine [[GEE-yoh-teen]]. The \"Reign of Terror\" was (*)</b> overseen by, for ten points, which radical lawyer and head of the Committee of Public Safety during the French Revolution?", "answer": "Maximilien <b><u>Robespierre</u></b> (or Maximilien Fran\u00e7ois Marie Isidore de <b><u>Robespierre</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>This painting, which was likely completed after</u></b><em><b><u> Parnassus</u></b></em><b><u> and</u></b><em><b><u> La Disputa</u></b></em><b><u>, is in</u> <u>the first of the four rooms decorated by its artist in the Apostolic (+)</u> Palace. This painting depicts figures as diverse as Ptolemy and Zoroaster, alongside a conversing Plato and Aristotle. (*)</b> For ten points, name this large Renaissance fresco by Raphael depicting the title ideal institution in an ancient Greek city.", "answer": "<em> The</em> <em><b><u>School of Athens</u></b></em> (or <em><b><u>Scuola di Atene</u></b></em>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b><u>One of this country's literary \"superfluous men\" fails to win the love of Tatyana</u> <u>after informing her that he will grow bored of marrying her. The creator of that</u> <u>character allegedly inspired the play</u></b><em><b><u> The Inspector General</u></b></em><b><u> by another author from</u> <u>this country. The author of</u></b><em><b><u> Eugene</u></b></em><b><u> (+)</u></b> <em><b>Onegin</b></em><b> was from this country, as was another writer whose epileptic son inspired the character Alyosha [[ahl-YOH-shah]] in</b><em><b> The </b><b>Brothers Karamazov</b></em><b>. Alexander Pushkin, Nikolai Gogol, (*)</b> and Fyodor Dostoyevsky are from, for ten points, which European nation?", "answer": "<b><u>Russia</u></b> (accept <b><u>Russia</u></b>n Empire or Imperial <b><u>Russia</u></b>; or <b><u>Rossiya</u></b>; do not accept or prompt on \"Soviet Union\" or \"U.S.S.R.\")", "metadata": "Literature - European Literature - Short Fiction"}, {"question": "<b><u>A man from this Protestant sect, William Prynne, wrote a scathing critique of</u> <u>mainstream religion called</u></b><em><b><u> Histriomastix</u></b></em><b><u>, condemning the excesses of Renaissance</u> <u>theatre. This movement's ban of (+)</u> Christmas celebrations led to riots in southeast England. This Christian sect, of which Oliver Cromwell (*)</b> was a member, dominated the early politics of colonial New England. For ten points, name this religious movement of the UK and the Thirteen Colonies which aimed to purge the Anglican Church of Roman Catholic traditions.", "answer": "<b><u>Puritan</u></b>s", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}